{"tossups": [{"question": "This program was aided by the studies of research teams under Bill Moyers and Richard Goodwin. This program was first described in a speech at Ohio University, where it was claimed that \u201cno child will go unfed, and no youngster will go unschooled.\u201d Poll taxes were outlawed under this program\u2019s Voting Rights Act. Medicaid and Medicare were established under, for ten points, what set of domestic welfare programs under Lyndon B. Johnson?", "answer": "<b> Great Society</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event produced a list of banned books known as the<em> Index Librorum Prohibitorum</em> and defined the Canon of the Bible to include the whole of the Vulgate and exclude Third and Fourth Maccabees. The papal bull<em> Benedictus Deus</em> upheld the doctrines produced by this meeting, which was presided over by both Julius III and Pius IV. This meeting set the number of sacraments at 7 and condemned the 95 Theses of Martin Luther. For ten points, name this 16th century church council that denounced the Protestant Reformation.", "answer": "Council of<b> Trent</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This war escalated when the desecration of the Hiera Orgas led to the passing of the harsh Megarian Decree. The Thirty Years\u2019 Peace failed to create a lasting end to this war. One side in this war aimed to use the port of Piraeus to supply itself while defending from within the Long Walls, but that strategy was thwarted after it lost at Aegospotami. Plague took the life of Pericles during, for ten points, what 5th century BC war between Athens and Sparta?", "answer": "<b> Peloponnesian</b> War", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A painting of this man also depicts Simon Fraser and many other people who weren\u2019t actually present at the historical event in question. In that painting, a Native American resting his head on his chin views this man in a position similar to that of Christ after the Crucifixion. This man wears a red army coat and is being attended by a kneeling doctor in a blue coat. A Benjamin West painting depicts, for ten points, what British general who died at the 1759 Battle of Quebec?", "answer": "James<b> Wolfe</b> (accept The Death of General<b> Wolfe</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This empire built sculptures of winged lions with human heads that were known as lamassu. Artifacts of this empire were excavated at Dur-Sharrukin, a former capital located in present-day Khorsabad. This empire besieged Hezekiah at Jerusalem during the reign of Sennacherib. A large ancient library was built by this empire\u2019s ruler Ashurbanipal. For ten points, name this Iron Age empire centered at Nineveh.", "answer": "Neo-<b>Assyrian</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s son founded the first settlement by Spain in Uruguay while exploring the Rio de la Plata. The John Day letter recorded this man\u2019s voyages, which were commemorated by a tower in Bristol, England. This man commanded the<em> Matthew</em> to Cape Bonavista. The Vikings had previously reached the land that this man explored, which lies near Cape Breton Island in Nova Scotia. For ten points, name this Genoan sailor who sailed for Henry VII to explore Canada for England.", "answer": "John<b> Cabot</b> (or Giovanni<b> Caboto</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of these devices was co-developed by the developer of the Heimlich maneuver and the original voice actor of Tigger. At Wayne State University, one of these devices was used in a surgery on Henry Opitek after he was found to be suffering shortness of breath. The first of these devices was invented by Vladimir Demikhov while experimenting on dogs. One of these devices designed by Robert Jarvik has tubing made of polyurethane and contains pneumatically-fuelled ventricles. For ten points, name this medical device, a manmade version of a critical organ.", "answer": "<b> artificial heart</b>s", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "This politician sent Robert Napier to rescue missionaries from Tewodros II in the punitive expedition to Abyssinia. Lionel de Rothschild loaned this man money to finance the purchase of the Suez Canal. This man authorized the Royal Titles act to name Queen Victoria as Empress of India and served as the only Jewish prime minister to date. For ten points, name this Conservative prime minister who rivaled William Gladstone in 19th century England.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Disraeli</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Near the end of this opera, the title character questions \u201cHow much of what we did was good?\u201d while pondering his old age. Within this opera, the whipping of a woman during a performance of<em> The Red</em> <em>Detachment of Women</em> shocks one character into rushing the stage to help; in response, another character sings the aria \u201cI am the wife of Mao Tse-Tung.\u201d For ten points, name this John Adams opera that depicts a landmark 1972 presidential visit to China.", "answer": "<b> Nixon in China</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "George Barnard collected a set of 61 prints in his<em> Photographic Views</em> of this campaign. A telegram in which a president said \u201cgo as you propose\u201d gave its leader permission to carry out this campaign, during which Orlando Poe was tasked with dismantling bridges. Special Field Orders Number 15 was issued after this campaign concluded with the capture of thousands of bales of cotton and a crucial port city. An estimated $100 million dollars in damage was caused by, for ten points, what campaign through Georgia led by William Tecumseh Sherman?", "answer": "Sherman\u2019s<b> March to the Sea</b> (accept<b> Savannah Campaign</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Ingvar Kamprad, the founder of IKEA, drew controversy by moving his production facilities to this country. This country liberalized under the leadership of Wladyslaw Gomulka [vlad-ee-slav go-moo-ka]. The wave of protests that eventually overthrew this country\u2019s Communist government began at the Lenin Shipyard. For ten points, name this Eastern European country where Lech Walesa [lek vah-wen-sah] led the Solidarity movement.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "At the beginning of this event, a cannon firing led to the release of 25,000 pigeons, many of whom defecated on the audience. Avery Brundage controversially pulled Marty Glickman and Sam Stoller out of participation in this event, where Louis Zamperini competed in the 5,000 meters and Luz Long competed against an African-American track and field star who won four gold medals. For ten points, name these pre-World War II Olympic games that were overseen by Adolf Hitler.", "answer": "19<b>36 Summer Olympics</b> in<b> Berlin</b> (accept any answer with<b> Olympics</b> and at least two of the other three underlined parts. Prompt on partial answers.)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This man, who was the first to reprint a Masonic book in America, compiled thirteen virtues in his unfinished autobiography. This ambassador to France obtained the letters of Thomas Hutchinson, and drew a political cartoon of a chopped-up snake with the words \u201cJoin or Die\u201d to support his Albany Plan. For ten points, name this Founding Father and author of<em> Poor Richard\u2019s Almanack</em>, who performed a famous kite experiment in a thunderstorm.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Franklin</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "<b>At this battle, Charles Wikoff and three other commanders were injured or killed in under an hour, leading Ezra Ewers to assume command. The winning side at this battle</b> <b>came under fire from Mausers at a location called (+)</b> <b>\u201cBloody Ford.\u201d Troops from El</b> <b>Caney provided support for this side\u2019s victors. Though the Buffalo Soldiers were prominent at this battle, it is more often associated with a (*)</b> cavalry unit that went on to fight at the Siege of Santiago. For ten points, name this 1898 battle in Cuba where Teddy Roosevelt fought with the Rough Riders.", "answer": "Battle of<b> San Juan Hill</b> (accept Battle of<b> San Juan Heights</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This work\u2019s first section prioritizes justice over convenience by using the example of a drowning man and a plank. This work\u2019s line \u201cunjust law is itself a species of violence\u201d was</b> <b>quoted by Mahatma Gandhi, who read it while (+)</b> <b>in jail in South Africa. This work was</b> <b>itself written in jail, as its author had been arrested for refusing to (*)</b> pay taxes in protest of slavery and the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this 1849 Henry David Thoreau essay that argues for opposition to unjust government.", "answer": "<b> Civil Disobedience</b> (or<b> Resistance to Civil Government</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This philosopher asked \u201cWhat is the meaning of ascetic ideals?\u201d in the third essay of a book</b><em><b> On the Genealogy of Morality</b></em><b>, which was a follow-up to</b><em><b> Beyond Good and Evil</b></em><b>. This</b> <b>thinker was horrified by the (+)</b> <b>\u201ceternal recurrence,\u201d and he thought that the \u201cwill to</b> <b>power\u201d was the driving force of life. This philosopher wrote a parable about an insane man with a lantern in (*)</b><em> The Gay Science</em>. For ten points, name this German philosopher who wrote<em> Thus</em> <em>Spoke Zarathustra</em>, an important influence on Nazism who originated the phrase \u201cGod is dead.\u201d", "answer": "Friedrich<b> Nietzsche</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Candice Bergen claimed that this man gave a \u201cperfectly intelligence speech\u201d [sic] when he criticized the show</b><em><b> Murphy Brown</b></em><b> for \u201cmocking the importance of fathers.\u201d After comparing his length of Congressional service to a former president, this man was scolded by (+) Lloyd Bentsen, who said \u201cSenator, you\u2019re no Jack Kennedy.\u201d Despite that incident, this man became (*)</b> vice president after the defeat of Michael Dukakis in 1988. For ten points, name this vice president who served under George H.W. Bush.", "answer": "Dan<b> Quayle</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "cted from a tree to make products like tires?", "answer": "<b> rubber</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Engineering"}, {}], "bonuses": []}